Guide to the Francisco Hernandez Maydagan Papers ALBA.300
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Francisco Hernandez Maydagan Papers
1937-1940
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Maydagan, Francisco Hernandez
ALBA.300
.25 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box
Francisco Hernandez Maydagan was born in Havana, Cuba in 1909. He traveled to Madrid in 1934 and volunteered to fight in the International Brigades on the side of the Spanish Republican Army. He was promoted to captain in December 1936, and was later transferred to the 41st Mixed Brigade in March 1937 and the 197th Mixed Brigade of the 52nd Division in 1938. The Francisco Hernandez Maydagan Papers (dated 1937-1940) includes 51 documents related to Maydagan's service in the International Brigades during the Spanish Civil War. Documents in this collection include military orders, letters between Maydagan and commanders, travel documents, receipts, and medical records. Many of these documents relate to Maydagan's travels throughout Spain and his hospitalization during the war.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased from Kevin Jackson in 2015; the accession number associated with the collection is 2017.010.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical / Historical
Francisco Hernandez Maydagan was born in Havana, Cuba in 1909. He traveled to Madrid in 1934 and volunteered to fight in the International Brigades on the side of the Spanish Republican Army. He was promoted to captain in December 1936, and was transferred to the 41st Mixed Brigade in March 1937. Maydagan was wounded several times during the war. In August 1937 he was hospitalized during the battle of Tereul, but resumed fighting in September of that year. He was later hospitalized again and was moved between several brigade hospitals. In 1938 Maydagan was fighting with the 197th Mixed Brigade of the 52nd Division. He returned to Cuba in 1939.
Scope and Contents
The Francisco Hernandez Maydagan Papers (dated 1937-1940) includes 51 documents related to Maydagan's service in the International Brigades during the Spanish Civil War. Documents in this collection include military orders, letters between Maydagan and commanders, travel documents, receipts, and medical records. Many of these documents relate to Maydagan's travels throughout Spain and his hospitalization during the war.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans.; Cubans.
- Promotion to Captain of Militia, 1936 December 31 (Box 1, Item 1)
- Receipt, 1938 (Box 1, Item 2)
- Safe Conduct Pass, International Brigade, 52 Division, Battle of Teruel, 1938 May 20 (Box 1, Item 3)
- Certification of Battle Wound, Francisco Maydagan of the 82nd Batallion, 21st Brigade, 1937 August 28 (Box 1, Item 4)
- Pacific Line Ticket to Havana, undated (Box 1, Item 5)
- Certification from the 197th Mixed Brigade of 52nd Division, undated (Box 1, Item 6)
- Letter Regarding Maydagan Request to Return to Battle, Army Corps XIX, 64 Division, 1938 April (Box 1, Item 7)
- Certificate of Membership in the Communist Party in Cordoba, 1936 (Box 1, Item 8)
- Passport Granting Maydagan Passage throughout the War Zone, 1937 July (Box 1, Item 9)
- Accreditation of Maydagan as Professor, 1939 February (Box 1, Item 10)
- Report on Maydagan's Health, Military Hospital in Cuenca, 1938 July (Box 1, Item 11)
- Military Travel Document: Route by Car to Barcelona, Valencia, and Madrid, 1937 August (Box 1, Item 12)
- Military Travel Document: Route by Car to Barcelona, 1937 September (Box 1, Item 13)
- Order from Coronel Martinez Carton to Maytagan, Battle of Tereul, 164th Division, undated (Box 1, Item 14)
- Courier Document: Certification of Communist Party Membership, Madrid Front, Column Somosierra, undated (Box 1, Item 15)
- General Mail: Somosierra Front, 5th Regiment of Popular Militias, 1936 September 30 (Box 1, Item 16)
- Certificate of Registration: International Brigades Military Hospital of Cuenca, Civil War, 1938 July (Box 1, Item 17)
- Medical Report: International Brigades Military Hospital in Valencia, 1937 September (Box 1, Item 18)
- General Mail: International Brigades, Defense Ministry, General Staff, Barcelona, 1937 September (Box 1, Item 19)
- Transfer of Command from Martinez Carton to Commander San Pedro of the 225 Mixed Brigade, XIX Army Corp, 1938 May 20 (Box 1, Item 20)
- Paper Flag: Republican Army, undated (Box 1, Item 21)
- Withdrawl of Republican forces from Girona, 1939 January 29 (Box 1, Item 22)
- Training in the Levante Army, 1938 (Box 1, Item 23)
- Madrid Front, 41st Mixed Brigade, 1937 March 9 (Box 1, Item 24)
- Transfer to 52nd Division, 197th Brigade, undated (Box 1, Item 25)
- Handwritten order for the 21st Mixed Brigade., 1937 August 27 (Box 1, Item 26)
- Cuban Communist Party Membership Certification, 1938 December (Box 1, Item 27)
- Transfer to the 67th Mixed Brigade, 1936 November (Box 1, Item 28)
- International Brigade, 4th Division, 36 Mixed Brigade., 1937 June 4 (Box 1, Item 29)
- Appointment to Command the 195th Mixed Brigade, 1938 July (Box 1, Item 30)
- Orders to the 21st Mixed Brigade, 1937 August 20 (Box 1, Item 31)
- Central Zone Document, Marked Personal, 1939 January 6 (Box 1, Item 32)
- Telegram to Maydagan from his Mother, March 26, 1939., 1939 March 26 (Box 1, Item 33)
- Safe Conduct Pass, 1938 July (Box 1, Item 34)
- Military Hospital Pass, Valencia, 1937 September 9 (Box 1, Item 35)
- Correspondence, 64th Division, 1938 April 4 (Box 1, Item 36)
- Meeting Request, 1937 July 30 (Box 1, Item 37)
- Receipt for Coat Purchased by Maydagan: 197th Mixed Brigade, 1938 November 10 (Box 1, Item 38)
- Governor of War Formally Requests a Visit from Maydagan, Captain 67th Brigade, 1937 March 29 (Box 1, Item 39)
- Receipt: Communist Party Membership Fee, 1938 August (Box 1, Item 40)
- Travel Pass: Madrid and Valencia, 1938 May 20 (Box 1, Item 41)
- Certificate of Health from Physician in Havana, 1938 January 6 (Box 1, Item 42)
- Certificate of Will, 1937 July 17 (Box 1, Item 43)
- Discharge Certificate: Military Hospital, Cuenca, 1938 May 8 (Box 1, Item 44)
- Confederación Nacional del Trabajo Field Hospital Diagnosis, 1936 January 1 (Box 1, Item 45)
- Column Somosierra, Junta Defending Madrid, 1937 January 1 (Box 1, Item 46)
- International Brigade Headquarters Admission, Valencia, 1938 December 27 (Box 1, Item 47)
- 52nd Division Document, 1938 July 23 (Box 1, Item 48)
- Purchase Document, Cordoba, 1938 October 7 (Box 1, Item 49)
- Document Granting Command of the 36th Mixed Brigade, 4th Division, 1937 June 14 (Box 1, Item 50)
- Maydagan's Cuban Passport, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Item 51)